okay welcome back and we're gonna do
some q a at the beginning of the class
because guessler can't stop his mouth so
uh we're gonna start with a question
here at diamond mountain
and then we'll go to questions online
so please feel free to send
any questions by the way when we do a q
a
it doesn't have to be relevant or
intelligent uh you can ask anything you
want
okay that's the fun part and I think we
already had somebody with a microphone
talk loud
one two three
possibility
um I had conversation with my llama
and my llama says that never ever due to
Glenn for your heart teacher
um but my karma forced me uh
see people and suffering and
unfortunately see my llama like Pearson
who can heal who can die
um what can I do uh to change this okay
good question uh so the question was uh
about doing Tongan with your teacher uh
and he's gonna talk about it on this
page he's getting to it already
but generally uh I'll I'll just go there
he says uh
in about
maybe today or tomorrow he says this is
the sentence he says
it means uh when you do the taking part
it's inappropriate to do it with your
teacher okay
or with a Buddha he says those two
and he says means there's nothing to
take
okay so uh
I I had the same problem you know with
my teacher I I lived with my teacher for
25 years he had a
like his teeth okay when I met him he
was 55 he had never been to a dentist
uh in 55 years and uh it was bad and uh
they didn't have Dennis in Tibet at that
time and uh so
you know I had to take him
to the dentist and uh the dentist said
he needs 20 teeth taken out
and uh
and he was afraid because he'd never
been to a dentist so I had
uh wisdom teeth
and I told the dentist take mine out
first he can watch and then he won't be
nervous and then it was very bloody and
messy and
they had to drill the teeth into pieces
and it got infected and and uh
so I had all this uh
I had this question too you know because
it seemed like he was really suffering
and uh so I think um
my own personal opinion is uh
with your teacher and with the diamond
way teachings you're gonna have to be
able to
uh
perceive your teacher
as ill or suffering and still believe
they are not
and and still take them to the dentist
and still make sure their teeth are in
good shape so a real diamond way
practitioner
has to overcome this uh division between
appearances and reality you know I I
I I feel a very serious responsibility
to make sure my llama's health is taken
care of and I spend a lot
I spend a lot of time on it
I spend a lot of time on arranging
doctors and stuff and uh
at the same time I don't perceive my
llama as needing a doctor
okay so I think you when you practice
Diamond way
uh
uh that's a something you're gonna have
to live with you know you have to get
you have to balance uh taking care of
your teacher's health
with all of your resources
and then on the other hand uh believing
that they are not sick
and that they are not really sick so
it's
it's that's one of the diamond way
practices you have to get good at
you know and so you have to
I'll tell you this how about this way
if you work the way you should work to
take care of your alumnus health
one day you will see that they don't
need it
how's that
okay
no work to take care of their health you
will never see that they don't need it
got it
how's that
uh other question Timothy you got some
online
yes so online
um there's been several questions I'm
going to combine it into one question
here there's several questions about
balancing priorities in life
so how do we balance one of the
questions is about how do we balance the
you know perhaps our Dharma life with
our work life or balancing taking care
of ourselves and taking care of others
and then asking the question and finding
the punsumba the third way so
the questions keep coming back to what
is the seed to be able to
not see this compartmentalization
so that we can actually see these
creative ways yeah look at it because in
class one of the questions says in the
class you're asking us to do it
what's the seed that will allow us to be
able to do it yeah good question
uh
yeah so look I understand that uh
I have to learn to
like taking care of others or taking
care of myself I understand that I need
to do both
and it doesn't feel like I have time
it feels like I have to sacrifice one or
the other
and you know I understand that there are
Buddhas who can do both at the same time
I'm not at that level
I I only have so many hours in a day I
only have two hands I only have I'm not
like
with a thousand arms or something
I I don't have that capacity so
uh I have to deal with my limited
resources and for example
uh it's very common for new Buddhists to
over buddhistise
and and burn out and then Quinn
and then they never come back and I've
I've if you're in the Dharma business
you've seen it a million times
and people get all excited about doing
Tong Lan or taking care of other people
and then they neglect their own health
they neglect their own family they
neglect their prior commitments that
they made before they met Buddhism like
a marriage
and they get in trouble so
if so the question is basically this if
if I'm a normal person
and I'm limited
with my time
then uh how do I
how do I manage my time and what are
some creative things I can do
to plant the seeds for punksumba to see
these third options you know and I'll
start with a
uh I went to a Tibetan doctor recently I
haven't been to a Tibetan doctor for
40 years or something and I translated
for one
two famous doctors the two most famous
modern
well 20th century
doctors I was their translators and uh
so and I remember the the first
doctor I translated for he gave a talk
at Nancy Karen's
part Loft in New York big these big
cheap
space is in dangerous neighborhoods and
uh
and she had a baby in her arms named
Alice
uh how old is she now 40
something
she's a doctor herself
uh anyway she was in the class in
Nancy's arms that's how old it was and
uh the uh the doctor was somebody said
What are the what gives people cancer
and he said oh many things that you guys
uh don't understand you know it's
he said I'll give you some things that
you don't even know you don't even think
about
the
do you did you ever buy new tires for
your car
and everybody said yeah I bought tires
for my car he says why did you buy new
tires for your car
and we're like because the tires wore
out he says when a tire wears out
where does the rubber go
and we're like I don't know
it wears off the tire in New York City
there's a million and a half people
commuting in every day
they drive in many of them then the
tires he says the rubber goes off the
tires it particulizes it gets into the
air in Manhattan you're breathing rubber
all day of course you're gonna get
cancer you know
and we're all like wow we never thought
of that and he says I'll tell you
another thing
you know this can your processed food
in plastic and cans it's it causes
cancer
you know the food in processed food
causes cancer he says you can't eat that
stuff You Gotta Eat fresh food
and uh and then he went on like that and
finally somebody raised their hand and
they said uh
you know
look I'm just a normal person
I live in a normal
apartment I go to a normal store I you
know I gotta eat something I gotta buy
something I gotta Breeze something
you know what am I supposed to do you
know and he gave some advice and he said
you know try to eat more fresh food
avoid putting your nose near the exhaust
of the cars and
and then he's and then he said then he
looked at me and he said and tell our
guy to stop using the word normal
and I'm like what and he said he said
it's bad luck to talk about yourself as
normal you know and I said well what do
you mean and he said nobody's normal you
are all amazing
you know and I'm like wait I thought you
were just teaching medicine you know and
he goes off on this thing and he says
the reason you get sick is because you
think you're normal that's the worst
thing you can do you know you are all
special your super special people you
heard Buddhism
you know you're the one person out of a
million who came to diamond mountain or
more uh you're like
nothing amazing you know you're you're a
special special people and he went
ranting he was ranting for like half an
hour on on this thing you know don't
call yourselves normal so that's my
advice for this question
is uh you know you say what how is a
normal person uh supposed to deal what's
the seeds you can plant
to
get the ability
to be more creative with your time and
to see what's the seeds you can plant to
see the
the possumas and and one important scene
is to stop thinking of yourself as
normal okay you are not normal
okay if you're here I'm lying
if you're here at Diamond Mountain
you are weird no I mean
no you're special
okay now you are
and you you guys you listen to these
sutras all day you know so gangs books
stuff like that
to meet those books is is one person out
of a hundred million you know to to hear
these teachings
the fact that you're here is proof
that you are special when you think
about it more often God plants the seeds
to see higher options
okay
okay so it's this
okay in the diamond way
it's it's a greater sin
to think of yourself as normal than to
kill another person
okay
all right
so if you kind of fix that one
you you'll see that you'll plant the
seeds to see those
those options third options okay
cool and that's
I'll tell you another thing about
Buddhism
the real antidotes for things are
totally fun
okay like when the real solutions to
problems
are totally fun
okay if you think a solution sounds
difficult or unpleasant or like drudgery
you're in the wrong place
you know because all the real all the
highest
solutions to problems are totally fun
okay and it's totally fun to
to realize how lucky you are you know
and
so
uh the best practices the highest
practices are the most fun
and if you're not having fun there's
something wrong what did
hundred dollars Dharma mitra's famous
quotation
[Music]
I want the whole thing
if you want the whole money I need the
whole quotation
like no yoga No Pain who said that
all right stop stop cancel the bed
cancel
Dharma Metro stand
no pain no gain no fun no yoga okay it's
it should be somebody should attach it
to the fourth chapter of the yoga Sutra
which they also attached to the Yoga
Center okay
actually Aisha gets it because she had
it in the chat before you canceled the
best Aisha that's true
okay 100 bucks for Aisha added to my tab
with Anatole
I owe Anatole some money
okay
all right
let's go back to the book uh
yeah so do think about that antidote
okay okay the seeds
kind of all-purpose scenes
is to realize how special you are and
how lucky you are
and and that's kind of all-purpose seeds
to see new solutions to your challenges
and those Solutions what's the Tibetan
word
for an unusual strategy
yeah
you should wait till I offer money okay
I got a free answer
thank you okay yeah it means uh skillful
means uh cool strategy
fun strategy
to solve problems okay
being a Buddhist should be fun if it's
not fun you're doing something wrong
all right here we go
is that where we are right
so he says gongbo here it's a very
unusual Tibetan word
that means a spirit a demon spirit that
took over your heart
okay like what do you call that like
voodoo
you know like somebody put a voodoo
spell on you and some
some Demon took over your heart you know
that's called gumbo okay
so he says
first of all I want you to think about
all the people in the hell realms
and I I I think of Ukraine with missiles
coming down you know like like that must
be a similar feeling I think it kind of
helpless
uh Terror
helpless Terror think of there are
beings uh who live like that in the hot
house in house
there's a funny
there's a Christian writer who's very
great very good to read oh what's his
name
C.S Lewis no is it yeah
uh what's the book
screw tape letters yeah screw tape is an
old word for the devil
and uh it's called screw tape letters
and it's a beautiful book of letters
from the
from the devil to his nephew
his nephew has come to Earth and he's
assigned to corrupt a young man
and uh and he keeps failing the young
man keeps being pure and the uncle's
getting really upset because his nephew
is not corrupting the guy very well and
and the C.S Lewis said it was very
painful to write the book
because he had to put his mind in the
devil's mind you know anyway the devil
is bragging in that book he says uh one
of the greatest achievements
of devils in modern times
is to make people feel
not modern
if they believe in hell
you know one of the greatest
achievements
of the devils in the world
is to get modern people to say there is
no hell or that hell is an old stupid
idea of abdante or the Catholic church
or something you know he's
he's like one of the greatest
achievements
of the forces of evil in this world
is to convince people that you are
stupid or corny if you believe in hell
you know and and it's really true
okay there is a place there is a place
like that and it's easy to go there and
it's hard not to go there
and they are suffering so
you take all that fire
all that fire all that confusion I mean
think of a
an apartment building burning from a
missile hit or something and then just
so it means you just sweep up all the
fire
in your arms like this you just embrace
the fire and you should jam it into your
heart
and you feed it to your that demon of
your selfishness okay it's really a
beautiful image whole apartment's on
fire whole apartment building is on fire
a missile just hit and you you you take
your arms like this and you go and
that's called
you know
and you jam it into your heart and you
feed it to your selfishness okay and
he's like um
and then it disappeared if they say it's
really important that it disappears
within a second okay
you don't keep it there and say oh look
my heart's burning okay all right you
have to put it out but before you take
the next breath
that fire should be gone
and it should have killed the demon
both are gone there's a practice my
teacher called it the cigarette smoke
practice
and the next moment after you feed the
fire to the demon the demon should
disappear
and my teacher said uh
Marlboro
should be like cigarette smokers
you know like on a on a windy day
like cigarette smoke the last part of
cigarette smoke just because and then
the demons gone
and the hell Realms are all comfortable
like that okay so cigarette smoke at the
end okay
last bit then all the selfishness is
gone okay so I'd like you to practice
that today
Yeah question loud
box blue box
thank you
do that with every breath we take and
give or we just take take and then in
the end
what was she asked with each breath
should I take it I don't think you can
do it with each breath I personally I I
I cook it for a while I think about it I
visualize the hell I get everything
ready I make sure I got a good Demon
here
and then then I'd like say okay go and I
go
you know and uh use your left nostril
for the inhale okay and that's a
pranayama
okay that's a tempting practice uh so
that's why we practiced it this morning
okay okay so when you're taking use your
left nostril
what if I have a cold
or a Sedona allergy
uh
then just imagine that it's coming to
your left nostril it's okay okay
uh
and then take it in and then do it you
know
cigarette smoke everything's done
relaxed for a while
enjoy have fun think about
the hell realm just became like really
nice place
like a like a very beautiful like a
diamond mountain
Green Day here in
and then if you feel like it do a second
one I I personally don't think you can
do two or more than two or three in a
session
it's also very emotional it's kind of
draining so
you know that you don't try to do it
with every single breath but you can
keep using your left nostril to take
okay
um
we're gonna do more detail on it and
it's coming okay
uh Denny says I want you to work through
the
so there's two there's two parts to hell
basically the worst part of hell has two
parts it's a hot hell in the cold hell
one is like the North Pole
one is just fire
they don't talk much about the cold
house but he says do the cold health and
we're going to do more detail in a
minute okay you dot uh take care of the
prathas
hungry ghosts okay
okay then take care of the dendrils the
animals
and take care of the
Min and the sauce these are like uh
worldly Gods worldly gods
and they look like Marvel
Comic characters
uh
and then the humans okay
and he says you can work up to the
suffering of bodhisattvas on the 10th
Buddhist
sometimes they say 10th level is
buddhahood sometimes they say level 11
is
okay so you can work your way up to high
body surface high body surface their
biggest problem is
called traces
name in
[Music]
traces subtle traces of problems that
they had
millions of years ago okay
okay like in the way they walk and stuff
okay weird weird little things
uh
dig deep so wrong number
[Music]
as soon as you do the taking
it's really important
to Duke that kind of uh dachshund yamchi
what's that
in general
yeah exchange yourself with others and
feel how it feels to those guys
they're like wow that's nice
you know thank you you know so put
yourself in their shoes
after the Lemba put yourself in the
shoes of the person
whose suffering you took away
and and
see how much it feels to them and it
doesn't hurt
to feel how grateful they feel towards
you
okay that's fine
that's fine okay okay so feel
after you do the Limba after you take
the problems from other people
briefly put yourself in their shoes and
feel how good it feels
and then
see how good it feels to be the hero
okay because they're looking at you and
saying oh my God you know you just put
an air conditioner in the hell room
you're you're so great you know
and and that's not a bad thing it's not
prime okay okay it's not Prime
it's a healthy
enjoying the good stuff you've done is
different from Prime
Pride
sign that you're having Pride about your
tongue man is when you get competitive
my my tongue lands better than robs you
know uh
and if you can do Tomlin without Pride
probably you're rejoicing and that's fun
and that's great
and I just cleaned out the hot house I'm
pretty cool literally
I can
all right
um
that's fine that's fine
uh so mapa means
it's it's important
to do that little exchange at the end
and see how nice it feels that hell was
emptied out
or that hell has become like diamond
mountain on a good day
okay all right and then he says
[Music]
and uh
there's also a side meditation you can
do
after you do uh and by the way I do want
you to do it today okay so you're taking
you're cleaning out the hell realms
then you're doing this the exchange and
you're looking at yourself as the hero
and and thank you very much
and then you're gonna tell the hell
realm guy
and by the way
uh I'm here to take the rest of your
crap also
okay I'm here to take the rest of your
bed sis
I will take them
okay if you have any more bad seats
lined up
for the future give me those now at the
same time let's clean out the whole show
you know I'm not just gonna clean out
your current hell Realm
uh you got any bad teeth left in there
you want to give me I'll I'll vacuum
cleaner
those also
and then you do this clever thing
where
every time something goes wrong for the
whole week you're like yay I used up
those extra bad things okay
because look
you're gonna have bad stuff happen this
week anyway
right until you're a Buddha this bad
stuff's gonna happen you're gonna have
disappointments
the car's not gonna start
you know the flight from Louisiana is
going to be late
stuff happens
and then you can say secretly in your
heart you can say ah I just used up a
few of that hell realm guys bad seeds
that I took then I vacuum cleaned okay
all right so then every other mess up
in your whole year
you can blame the other guy's teeth okay
and you can congratulate yourself you
know hey my car didn't start good job
you know hey my boss yelled at me Yay
good job
Ronnie
burned them too yeah you're supposed to
burn them and he says that
very important to believe that both you
and the other person don't have them
anymore but
if stuff goes wrong in your life
for the next
10 years you know you can you can
imagine that this is how the seeds are
burned okay
and it's a good way to
to use
it's a good way to get something out of
the problems you have anyway
okay it's a it's a good way to make
something useful out of them okay okay
so you're gonna clean out three steps
for this afternoon right clean out the
hell realms
what's the second one
look see how good it feels for them when
they look at you
and then for dessert
tell them by the way if you got any more
Bad Seeds left over get hand me those
let me take those two
you know I'll uh use them up in the next
few weeks
at my black hole cafe or something
hey Don Cafe
why do they call black holes Ellie Ellie
can tell you okay uh
next
how much time I got Tim nine
oh we're good okay
there's where he says look when you take
the suffering from other people don't do
it with your teacher and don't do it
with the Buddha okay
there's a famous Shanti Deva thing about
teachers
[Music]
and uh
there was a specific question in the
long room
which was
what do I do if my teacher is attacked
if my teacher is attacked do I have the
right to do violence to protect them and
I think it was he gets he gets irritated
and he says look if your teacher's a
teacher they don't need you
to protect them so just forget it okay
if someone's trolling
your teacher or someone physically
attacks your teacher
then or verbally attacks your teacher
that's not your business
the teacher can take care of their
teacher don't worry about it okay it's
very beautiful okay Okay so
you don't have to do Tomlin on your
teacher you know
they don't need it okay yeah
I have a question to clarify but can you
do it online with your teacher oh sure
you can sit together and take the hell
Realms fire away that's fine
so much yeah yeah
that's what we're doing okay uh
so there's no need to in Buddhism
we don't have this thing of you can do
violence if you're protecting your
teacher or something like that there's
no such thing
okay you can't do violence to anybody
um
now it goes a very beautiful Direction
and he says
uh kazaki regla he says look there's
many kinds of people in the world and
there's many different personality types
Rick means personality type
[Music]
also people's mental capacity their
spiritual capacity is
difference different people like I don't
know
[Music]
irritating people they don't rarely do I
get angry rarely my my specialty is
jealousy or desire
see so we all specialize
some of us specialize in everything
it says
learn everybody's got different
personalities okay so he says there's
gonna be late damn boy
so lay means karma in tibetan but it
also means work so late means beginner
a beginner okay he says if you're a lady
[Music]
he says look there's people
who are just starting out in Buddhism
and they're not ready even for thornland
okay they can't do it okay it's gonna
it's gonna hurt them to try to take the
pain from other people they're already
having a bad day
then uh tell them to take away other
people's problems they're like look I'm
I'm already having a breakdown I can't
handle any more problems and says okay
there's those kind of days there's days
when you're not gonna do it you know my
yoga teacher David Swenson he's like
there's days when you get on the
mountain you should just get off the map
I like those things
and uh it's just not gonna work today
okay he says so what if you're that kind
of person or what if you're having a bad
day and you don't feel like going to the
hell Realms today because you're already
having a hard day
then he says I got a meditation for you
okay so that the alarm Rim goes off on
another thing here's the meditation
picture
on yourself
if you're having a bad day
you can handle doing thumb land on
somebody else
then okay just do tunneling on yourself
okay
and by the way if Pabon corinthate was
here he'd say that's fine
you know we all got days when Tong lens
too much
you don't have to go visit the hell
realm every day
you know there's days like tax days
coming up right April 5th we got a
financial
no they they oh it's not the 15th
anymore
oh there's this and anyway
it's enough stress this week that we
don't need more stress I got the IRS I
don't need the hell around you know uh
so you can go you can go there okay you
can do tunnel in on yourself okay
and I'd like you to practice that also
today okay okay so uh you're gonna do
hell realms three parts right
and we're gonna describe
how to do donut on yourself
and and here's here's the instructions
for it and it's it's very beautiful okay
if you're having a day like that
some
he says go back to the seven part Mojo
and he quotes uh a line from the seven
part lojo
and it says
means when you're doing the land the
taking
in dongland giving and taking you're
allowed to start from yourself
means start with yourself okay if you're
having a hard day
or personally uh like in my three-year
Retreat which I did close to here
uh
my my personal observation maybe cat can
tell you uh
my meditation ability decreases as the
day goes on my best meditations are in
the
right after Dawn
and then I the mid-morning is really
good
after lunch is hopeless evening is more
hopeless
you know the Mind meditation the
building goes like this you know so he
says maybe if you're
and some people are worse in the morning
and better in the evening so but
judge judge the time of day judge your
mental
freshness and react to that do do it on
yourself if you're not feeling very
fresh
uh but you want to get some meditation
in then do it on yourself do Thumb in on
yourself and then maybe a couple hours
later you're gonna feel better
after your green drink oh
okay here's how to do it
uh in the morning
meditate on yourself this evening
okay in the future okay me in the future
okay like I know I'm I might have a
potential suffering coming up this
evening
uh
my friends Ellie and Adriana
and Rebecca offered to bring me a sample
from the new Indian restaurant in Bowie
which is risky
so
I can do Tong Lan on myself later
with the stomachache from the food
uh senior means so you can in the
morning
you can do tonglan on potential problems
that I hope I won't have in the evening
okay
and you can take away the pain in the
evening like I get tired I would like to
I know around nine o'clock or something
I can't I can't work that well and I
could take I could take the
take my own suffering okay
uh
and that's what the lojang says okay uh
that's the big letters down below you
guys
going
yeah there
okay
here's the original launch okay I always
like to go get it this is from the
12th century probably
when the text says
start your taking practice from yourself
Chima pandang Tana you can start with
the suffering you're going to have in
your next lifetime
but if you're not up for that
you could just start with the problems
you might have tomorrow
and you can take them today okay that's
the ancient
texts again
what's tropo in tibetan
po means friend so he says in this way
your future problems can become your
buddies
it's a it's a cute
it's very in kadampa
your future problems will become your
friends
you know like that okay you talk so cute
all right
next picture
I love this picture I use this picture
when I think about bodhichitta the first
body to the experience
it's the closest picture I've ever seen
to that experience and um
so we're going to talk about expanding
that
taking
to other planets okay
expanding this taking and giving and
taking to other planets
uh here we go
you could take this evening's problems
this morning
I I'd like this especially if I have a
meeting with someone that I know is
going to be tense
uh and I did this in my corporate career
like if I knew I was meeting with a
difficult supplier
in the afternoon
I would do Tomlin in the morning
and then when the meeting with the
difficult supplier comes in the
afternoon
subconsciously you remember taking away
the tension
and there's less tension or there's no
tension it's kind of cool so if you have
a difficult meaning coming up
or I don't know some emotionally
difficult thing
coming up
then on yourself
and get ready and what happens is in the
morning you do the thumb then
and you visualize the meeting in the
afternoon
and the suppliers yelling at you and
you're like okay I know I'm sorry and
you know and then you suck the tension
out of you
and give it to you this morning and you
destroy it right
and then frankly you won't remember
uh in the hours in between okay I used
to do this every day for corporate life
I would do it until 9 in the morning on
myself
and then I would forget about it and and
then at four o'clock the supplier comes
and suddenly I would feel
somebody taking away the tension
okay so it's a really cool practice okay
so in the morning
uh take away
some tension you expect in the afternoon
then you won't remember because you're
busy and then when you hit the afternoon
and the guy walks in suddenly the
tension's gone
it's like someone sucked it with a
vacuum cleaner so it's really cool
I I don't know if it's a subconscious
suggestive thing I don't know but it
works and uh
and uh the proof is in the pudding do
you know this American expression
it means uh
don't believe me just try it and you
will see
and it works and uh and it helped grow
my company it helped grow the company to
to ten thousand people from three
you know
this
practice of uh dealing with a problem in
your imagination in the morning
and then when you get to the problem in
the afternoon it there's some strange
stuff goes on like the supplier comes in
and tells you how sweet you are and
you're like what
you know I mean real stuff happens
because it's all coming from you anyway
right so you're messing with the seeds
in your mind for the afternoon okay in
the morning you're messing with the
seeds in your mind that are gonna create
the afternoon that and it's it's a fun
practice as I said
no pain no gain no fun no Buddhism
okay if you're not having fun you you
gotta
do more long room or something okay all
right um
you can also take away
problems next month
low Gemma next year
rest of your human existence this one
next life's problems
okay take away next I don't know why we
got this picture okay
[Music]
all of your future lives why not go for
the big time
you know all your future lives up to
Buddha
okay
uh Channel 10. then start on your paw
and your ma
your APA and your Amma okay then start
on your dad and your mom you covered all
your problems up to the end of your
human existence or your non-booted
existence
so why not start with your mom and your
dad okay
then
means friends and family
friends and family okay
work on them
damn Parma Pargo means
in between life between death and
rebirth but Parma means neutral people
in your life people you see at the
grocery store
people you see at the gas station on the
way to Diamond Mountain
okay just people you people you're never
gonna meet again soon
do it on them
Dan what's the ultimate
Jobs
means enemy Destroyer right Dom means
enemy
Ari Ari in
in Sanskrit
I artian sounds good not like Hebrew
already means the enemy
Destroyer
all right uh duh work on your enemies
and then uh some Jen Tom jacobar jump
keep going until you cover every living
creature
but I want you today
uh to practice it with yourself
tomorrow let's say okay or this evening
okay if you're doing it this morning
yeah just work on yourself I I'd like
you to have this
uh fallback meditation when you're
having a lousy day
and the meditation just isn't working
then then go to this one just
just take your own evenings problems
away and that's enough okay
okay uh don't stay in a bad meditation
for an hour
okay lighten it up brighten it up or
quit
okay but don't get to hate they say in
tibetan don't get too
hate your meditation scene
you know if it's if it's really not
going well dumb it down dumb it down
dumb it down quit
okay
don't quit every day
all right that's not many things
foreign
that's a misspell that's a miscarving in
the book uh it's
k-y-i-n okay
which is a very rare word
uh
so uh
kin is an is a very unusual word that
means uh
keep uh keep raising the bar
keep keep doing it kin means present
participle keep
raising the bar as soon as you can do
uh one person like your mom then
increase it to your dad and once you can
do it with your mom and dad increase it
to your family once you can do it with
your family do it with people you don't
know like that keep raising the bar
keep keep taking things
uh now we're ready for that image you
guys
that's the ultimate one right
and uh
he says
he says you can work up
through yourself
this evening yourself tomorrow yourself
this month yourself this year yourself
the rest of this life yourself the rest
of all your lives start with your mom to
go to your dad go to your relatives go
to your friends go to people you never
met or cared about and then go to
he says work up gradually build up your
strength okay Junkie
don't do it with your done
don't start with your enemy because you
won't be able to do it wholeheartedly
don't start with your enemy okay but
making a goal have it as a goal
and by the way when you start doing your
enemies your whole life gets turned
upside down
you know then it it's weird life becomes
weird
because you're taking care of your
enemies instead of competing with them
or hoping that they fail and life gets
strange
okay
then then it then you don't have any
enemies after a while or it's difficult
to call someone your enemy
you spent the whole morning trying to
take away their pain and then you're
supposed to fade them in the afternoon
it's it gets difficult
okay
[Music]
okay next picture
uh in English it's called what hopscotch
and it's I don't know they don't teach
it to boys in the 1960s but um
I guess it's some kind of thing where
you jump from one box to another
and uh it's a game it's a children's
game in America
and uh
we call it uh skipping okay it's a
Buddhist practice we referred to it with
the uh Lion's dance
where you jump you skip around
to different levels of meditation okay
okay so you can do a meditation
where you focus on one thing for an hour
or something like that
but there's also meditation practices
where you can purposely Jump Around
with control
okay with control
it's like a runner
who runs hard then stops slow faster
medium like that
I didn't do these running machines
they have a workout I I we had one in
Kyoto
I forget who it was it was Sadie or
somebody on a bicycle
and they had a
like a 20-foot TV screen and the guy was
was it you Tim oh it was him the guy's
like ah let's go faster and Tim's like
and then they're like let's slow down
into them and then uh it's like you jump
into different gears you know and that's
that's called skipping meditation
okay by the way we're gonna have an
idiom examination
Adam means these idea images uh it's a
new word I invented
so the Examination for this class
I'm going to show you pictures and say
what are they
okay
so you should be making notes
you know we're on 15 now by the way
you've had you've had 15 pictures
and the
personally I can remember the content of
a of a teaching for a week if I have the
pictures
and I test myself at home
I say okay Hopscotch what's hopscotch I
say oh that's where you skip around to
different levels of tongman
right in one session you jump around to
different kinds of atonement
the last picture
what was the last picture we're gonna go
backwards you guys
we're skipping
yeah this is Sunland on your
enemy okay back one more you guys this
is spread it spread it from what to what
do the Tongan on
start with
yeah start with this evenings yourself
or this afternoon's yourself and then
work up to all the planets in the
universe okay last picture
yeah
especially if you're having a bad day
okay if it's just not gonna work you
have a choice get off the meditation
cushion
or dude don't land on someone who really
needs it
which is me
okay what's the one before that
not getting cut by Mr Robbie uh yeah
that's that's our Target the five Realms
yeah
microphone
I understand how we can do
cells because
we are the source of our own seeds but
how do we
how does Tomlin work with taking other
people's seats when we know that they
have the power to change their own seats
and not us
yeah good uh
that that gets into a deep question can
you really take pain from other people
uh can you really remove their pain and
and in my opinion the answer is no
you cannot
okay it's not gonna do anything to
lessen their pain
if you imagine you're taking away their
seeds
okay you
seeds are by definition personal
you cannot take other people's seats if
it was possible we wouldn't be here
we'd be in a Buddha Paradise already
okay if it was possible
to take away another person's Bad Seeds
we wouldn't be here
I mean that's just a
Buddhism loves lodging and that's I'm
afraid that's totally logical
you know so if it was possible to take
away somebody's seeds somebody would
have done it already okay
uh but the desire
to take away other people's seeds can
result in an environmental ripening
where you see lessons and that's
actually a ripening of yourself that
gets into a deeper question
of the five scanners
so the five skandas are the five parts
to a person in English we call it body
and mind
uh in Buddhism we call it the five parts
okay okay uh so and they are like this
body and mind
so body is the first part
then your feelings
capacity for discrimination all the
other parts of your mind and personality
and then your awareness these five these
are in Buddhism this is body and mind
body and mind okay
okay uh they're called The Body Mind
complex there's a beautiful debate in
the abidharma how big is this one
some people say it stops at the edge of
your skin then is like what about
fingernails
then they say well if you clip it and
you don't ouch that's not you
when you're clipping and you're ouch
that's too close
that's you that's the edge of you okay
and then other people say come on that's
ridiculous you know uh the things that
are happening in this room are affecting
me also so so actually in the abhi
Dharma in the deepavi Dharma the first
of the body and mind this body includes
the whole physical world
the universe okay
the this body and mind is the body is
everything
every physical thing okay so when you
take care of
yourself or when you when you take some
when you try to take someone sees the
environmental karmic result is that you
change the physical Universe because
that is part of you
got it
cool
so are you changing other people no are
you changing them yes
[Laughter]
thank you yeah but because they because
you created them
you created them with their sins
go continuing but if I don't finish my
uh quota from Tim it's your fault
no go ahead go ahead
in 20 years blame me
uh so my question is uh I understand
that by changing myself I stopped seeing
sufferment of other people
but is it because they stop suffering or
just something changes and I stop seeing
it
oh that's a good question
um
if you and that's the same question if
if you work on your own seeds
uh you are also changing because of this
because
the whole world is part of you you're
also changing the whole world yeah so
when you work on your own seats you are
working on other people's seats because
okay cool
yeah
uh okay
I was having fun going back to the
pictures what was the Mr Robbie haircut
yeah take it kind of how to cut that
black let's keep going back are you up
for it who's running that
okay what's the next one
I'm going back
let me do it this way
oh sorry hang on
okay good
um
the one before that is the guy with the
present I think
yeah what's that
foreign
[Music]
yeah but did anyone say give first yes
you know some people say give first
yeah
okay all right uh I forget the argument
for giving first
I'm arguing for taking first is obvious
it's the bicycle Band-Aid thing but
but yeah okay
okay next one
yeah especially with the Viewpoint
looking backwards after you switched
right
how does it feel
how you do guys are going good let's do
the last first summon
next one
wait
yeah four river cruise
image come on
the person already got thrown in the
remember
for yeah there's four steps to the
process they got thrown in the river
first they got handcuffed
they've got put in a cage and it was
dark
nice you guys were listening Audrey
all right uh next one
no it shouldn't be yeah
yeah this one
yeah what's it mean
yeah in uh
yeah okay in American English
uh we have this thing called ticket you
know he's my ticket to heaven or she's
my ticket amateur
okay like other people are your ticket
take care of other people you get what
you want
okay all right what's the one before
that
uh we didn't do this when I picture I
think but can you guess
it's when you eat a croissant
yeah go backwards take the process
backwards through the whole chain and
you will reach the people who invented
farming
fifty thousand years ago
we could be able to go back what's a
parallel meditation
deeper
yeah
the history of your thoughts
and again I tell you
that much
every day you will have really weird
stuff
no I mean you'll be able to go back to
your
when you were a baby and then you'll be
able to go back further and it's very
exciting and very sexy it makes you want
to meditate
you know you just follow it straight
back yes Mr chair
I I can repeat
I'm sure you mentioned that this one is
good for your emptiness
understandingness can I help you to see
entrance directly why is it
um working like that it gets you back
well the okay the main content
of a chicken Contin is you you will find
it easier
to to go back
even to previous life
the events that pop out first are every
Dharma teaching you ever got
and that helps you see emptiness
okay when you trace your mind back
to your childhood and your previous
lives the events that will come up first
and the strongest events the strongest
seeds in your mind are every teaching
you ever heard and you'll have this
weird experience of
remembering teachings that you went to
in your past life
that helps you see internet
and those are the most those are the
most
indelible seeds those seeds are there in
everybody
your past Dharma classes are there
but and if you do this practice you'll
hit those
uh one before that
yeah it's just kind of aspiration okay
are there people who have given their
bodies to Tigers yes should you try it
today no okay very bad idea
okay just try to give away your green
drink
and and what the book says is
you know have an aspiration may I one
day be like this
previous life of Lord Buddha
uh me and Christy
who helps found this place Christy
mcnelli my my old partner
who worked really hard to build this
place and probably most of the cabins
are her fault uh we used to go to the
McDonald's
and the only thing we could eat with
french fries
and we used to buy french fry and we
would go outside and we would break
pieces of french fries and and throw
them to The Sparrows
and we'd say uh we did this we had this
special McDonald's prayer and it was
if you eat that french fry you're gonna
be one of my first students after I
become a Buddha so that's a great
practice you can do you know you can
you can do that uh that's the tiger
thing okay okay like someday I I'll give
you my body but let's start with a
little bit of french fries okay uh after
I had a couple myself
um
and what's the first picture we had
oh
what is that one
no I think we didn't
I must be confused
no this should be one of uh
somebody cut yeah my brother cutting
what's that
that's the art of sharing
the interfering okay let's go back to
which which one were we on
I think it was
yeah 15. uh yeah the Hops guys okay we
got uh five minutes let's use it um
then I'll cover their long neck parts
so
if you're in that kind of a mood that
you not really into meditating today
start with doing tone in on yourself in
the afternoon or the evening and because
you're so interested in
yourself it'll be more fun okay
[Music]
then sometimes
Hopscotch to every living being up to
10th level buddhistophers
[Music]
sometimes you could do a geographical
version I'll start in Arizona I'll go to
California work my way up to Vancouver
you know stuff like that you can do a
geographical one
company
[Music]
or sometimes you can do the opposite and
start in Vancouver and come back Seattle
San Francisco L.A
Palm Springs
Gila bin
and get the Rimrock okay
[Music]
and then he says I want you to get to
the point where you could take the
suffering away from an animal that was
scared by a human
in
if you're sensitive
by the way his example is throwing a
rock at a dog but uh
if you're sensitive
watch the birds around here
in uh
you know you go out and they sound so
beautiful you know I record them for
Veronica send them to him send them to
her on the phone because they're so
beautiful but try to get close to one
and they wisely
Fly Away
and there's a reason why they do that
because they die if they don't you know
they so they are suspicious animals are
by the way if you do this for your
retreat
after six months of Silence they they
start trusting you
and we had coyotes we had
we'd have pet rabbits we had
rattlesnakes skunks all kinds of fun
things
they trust you after about six months if
you don't part I don't know what's the
thing
so anyway uh he says
next time you look at a bird
and they glance at you like that because
they don't trust you
do a quick thumbelin on their
nervousness to be near you
like get get your tongue line so refined
that you can take away a nervous glance
from a sparrow
I'm a momentary nervous glance from a
sparrow and get to the point where
you see a sparrow a little bit
uncomfortable take it take it and then
move on with your day
it's very beautiful
all right uh one more thing we have two
minutes next picture
he says
he says when you take
the
sparrows momentary
nervous
response to you when you take even that
much from another being you are not
allowed to set it on the table
what's he gonna say next
I want to see it strike your heart
okay every pain you take from another
person struck this is the only place you
can put them
okay don't say I'll pick you up tomorrow
you know I'll I'll put you in my heart
tomorrow
right away Let It Strike your heart
burn it here
okay you're not allowed to take a
pain from another person and say you
know I'm just gonna put that in the
fridge until tomorrow and then I'll then
I'll destroy it in my heart he says the
only place you're allowed to drop
a pain in an act of taking from another
person is in your own heart you're not
allowed to put it anywhere else okay
straight to the middle of your heart you
know always to the middle of your heart
day knock it say done
oh this is misspelled
uh it's totally misspelled
you should hire me to fix all this
oh you did
um
it's not d-a-n-g it's
d-n-g-a-n-g no
it's a very rare word and it means to be
it means to feel apprehensive
okay it's apprehensive then go back to
the picture
okay uh he says and the last thing he
says is if you're doing your thumb run
right
and if all those even the little Pains
of The Sparrows is and you're shoving it
in the right place in your heart it
should feel a little
scary
you should feel a little scared and then
he's gonna say tomorrow when we meet
again
that's a good thing
that means you're doing it right okay if
it feels a little bit uncomfortable
uh to take that fear of a bird into your
heart
you put it in the right place
you got you Ned and number what's that
foreign
yeah you have struck the right spot you
hit the chakra and then you hit the
Chuck and nail on the head
okay got it okay cool
we'll continue with that tomorrow